Guide to the Alfred Augustus Reed Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Alfred Augustus Reed papers
1845-1865
MS 411
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9
Correspondence and account books relating to Reed's activities in Batavia, Netherlands East Indies, as a representative of Paine, Stricker & Company of Amsterdam, a trading company. Correspondents include his wife, Caroline Suzette van Son Reed (1825-1861); the Band, Cramerus, Hasselman, van Alphen, and van Braam families, to which he was related by marriage; and Cramerus & Company, Amsterdam. Includes material relating to service and charitable projects in which Reed participated.
Reed, Alfred Augustus, 1817-1878
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. William Gordon Reed, 1964.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Alfred Augustus Reed papers consist of twenty-nine boxes of correspondence and account books dealing with the personal and business life of Alfred Augustus Reed (1817-1878). The span of the collection is 1845 to 1865. The bulk of the collection is comprised of correspondence relating to his commercial activities as a businessman and entrepreneur in the Netherland East Indies, based in Batavia on the island of Java.
Alfred Augustus Reed became the Batavia representative of Paine, Stricker & Co. of Amsterdam in 1845. He was one of the few major non-Dutch businessmen active in the East Indies. With his marriage in 1843 to Caroline Suzette van Son (1825-1861), Reed had established family ties with the van Braam, Band, van Alphen, Hasselman, and Cramerus families, all of which were prominent in the commercial or political life of Java (see van son genealogy below, in print version only). These family relationships were of great value to Reed in his trading career, and these names appear frequently in the correspondence.
Alfred A. Reed was active in the Java trade until the end of 1857, when he returned to Boston. From that time until 1865, he continued to maintain commercial relations with the Netherland East Indies through Paine, Stricker & Co. and Cramerus & Co., both ofAmsterdam. Alfred Reed was also very active in the social life of the Western community in Java. He participated in a number of service and charitable projects including the drive to establish a secondary school, in Herwijnen.
A large portion of the collection consists of packets and notebooks into which letters to and from Reed have been sewn or glued. These letters are in general, but not exact, chronological order. The packets have been divided into smallerunitsbut have been left in their original order for the most part. The distinction made by Reed in organizing the packets into Java and Europe-America correspondence and into business and family correspondence has not been careful, particularly since Reed had family ties with many business associates. Further, the Europe and America packets contain letters from correspondents abroad, some in the United States, but mainly in Singapore, Manila, Canton, Hong Kong, Macao, Calcutta, Madras, Cape Town, Amsterdam, and Paris. The material in the collection is in English and Dutch, with the largest part of the correspondence relating to Java, in the latter language.
The papers were the gift of Mrs. William Gordon Reed in 1964. For further information concerning Alfred Reed and these papers see the article by Robert van Niel in the register file.
Biographical / Historical
Alfred Augustus Reed: representative of Paine, Stricker, & Co. of Amsterdam in Batavia, Netherlands East Indies, from 1845 to 1857; returned to Boston where he retained commercial relations with the firm until 1865.
For a chart outlining the genealogical relations of the Van Son family, please consult the Genealogical Chart.
Business; Dutch -- Indonesia; Shipping; Amsterdam (Netherlands) -- Commerce; Asia; Indonesia -- Description and travel; Indonesia -- Economic conditions; Indonesia -- History -- 1798-1942; Java (Indonesia) -- Description and travel; Netherlands -- Colonies -- Indonesia; Account books; Businessmen; Reed, Alfred Augustus, 1817-1878; Reed, Caroline Suzette van Son, 1825-1861; Cramerus & Company; Paine, Stricker & Company
- Inventory
  Scope and Contents
  (*) Re: Europe and American correspondence, the collection retains the original designation of Europe and American letters. These letters are from correspondence abroad, some in the United Stetes, but mainly in Singapore, Manila, Canton, Hong Kong, Macao, Calcutta, Madras, Cape Town, Amsterdam, and Paris.
  - Java correspondence
    - 1845 Jul-1847 Dec (Box 1)
    - 1848 Jan-1849 Dec (Box 2)
    - 1850 Jan-1851 Feb (Box 3)
    - 1851 Mar-1853 Jul (Box 4)
    - 1853 Jul-1854 Jan (Box 5)
    - 1854 Jun-1856 Jun (Box 6)
    - 1856 Mar-1857 Sep (Box 7)
  - Europe and America correspondence (*)
    - 1845-1851 (Box 8)
    - 1845-1856 (Box 9)
    - 1854-1857 (Box 10)
  - Householdand business accounts, 1850-1857 November (Box 11)
  - Letterbooks
    - 1846-1852 Jul (Box 12)
    - 1852 Jul-1856 Mar (Box 13)
    - 1856 Apr-1857 Oct (Box 14)
    - 1857 Nov-1859 (Box 15)
  - Paine, Stricker & Co. correspondence
    - 1857 Dec-1858 Dec (Box 16)
    - 1860 Jan-1861 Dec (Box 17)
    - 1862 Jun-1864 Feb (Box 18)
  - Business correspondence
    - 1857 Dec-1859 Dec (Box 19)
    - 1860 Jan-1862 Mar (Box 20)
    - 1862 Apr-1863 Dec (Box 21)
    - 1864 Jan-1865 Dec (Box 22)
  - Business accounts, 1857 December-1865 September (Box 23)
  - Letters from family and friends
    - 1857-1859 (Box 24)
    - 1860-1862 (Box 25)
  - Herwijnen Project (Box 26)
  - Cassius Darling estate; Cramerus & Co., correspondence and accounts (Box 27)
  - Letters and accounts of Lemahabang Sugar factory (Box 28)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Journal of Java trip, 1850 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Article about Java (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Pictures (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Almanac, 1852 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Passport (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Printed articles (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 29, Folder 7)